so there's this really common view
nowadays that stream entry is attainable
without a major degree of restraint that
basically you only need to keep the five
precepts and uh you know live a more
life don't do the the obvious bad stuff
and that sense restraint and celibacy
and all these things are for for MKS or
for people who are striving higher than
just rentry and uh you know the proof
for that supposedly
is that people in the sutas uh these lay
people were getting the right view uh in
the Buddhist time despite the fact that
they were clearly living with their with
their spouses and uh you know enjoying
their wealth and and all that stuff so
but what people fail to see is that
there is a very big difference uh in
terms of both what those people had that
we don't have and what something that we
have that they don't have uh which is
not necessarily a good thing um and uh
it's even even if you actually read
carefully the descriptions that the
sutas give of the you know the the The
Wider context within which those
attainments of the Right View were
happening for those
people uh you will see first of all that
many of them had never met the Buddha so
they were talking to him for the first
time and uh second of all they were
they heard one discourse and they got
The Right View after that
so furthermore you also see what what is
exactly the suas themselves say what is
exactly um the thing that allowed the
Insight of the four noble truths to take
root in their minds and it's every
single time it says the Buddha was
giving them a talk on virtue on the
basic virtue like living moral life that
uh leads to you know rewards in the next
life and so on and then he went on to
describe the dangers of sensuality like
even of the next life of of anything uh
that is
um like the the the danger even in those
heavenly rewards that you would get out
of that uh uh keeping with five precepts
for example and then they say that when
their minds were actually withdrawn that
they were uh free from hindrances
specifically which mainly means sensual
desire then uh the Buddha went on to teach the
then uh the Buddha went on to teach the
four noble truths and uh then you know
they understood it and and and became
soas but the thing is uh people fail to
see specifically and most most
importantly what it means for the mind
to be free from hindrances as is s to
say so uh fundamentally one of the main
so uh fundamentally one of the main
wrong views today is that you know your
mind is free from hindrances when you
happen not to be thinking about objects
at the moment or you you happen not to
be angry or whatever but the hindrances
are much deeper than that the hindrances
are on the level of like your most
fundamental state of
being so to put it concisely it's
so to put it concisely it's
inconceivable for a person who has any
sort of even remotely like a
of even remotely like a
value a view that sensuality is
valuable uh to be free from the
hindrance of sens desire because that is
what the hindrance essential desire is
even if at the moment you are completely
focused on your bodily Sensations and
you're you're not thinking
supposedly if you are capable of
valuing uh sensal objects if they were
to arise regardless of whether they have
Arisen at the moment your mind is not
free from sensual desire at that moment
so um the hindrance is still there
regardless of whatever special
meditation pleasure you might be having
which by the way was not it was not even
a factor like these meditation
techniques were not even a factor in in
uh you know the the the procedure
leading up to that uh attainment of the
right view for those late people back in
the day so they were not doing any of
that at all uh and uh neither there nor
before uh evidenced by the fact that
they were following many of them were
following the views of other teachers
who didn't even teach meditation so um
the the the the thing the point I'm
trying to make is the thing that
actually um withdraws your mind from the
hindrances is actual dispassion towards
sensuality so for those people since
their minds were uh
naturally you could say
pure uh they didn't need as much of of a
you know a a discreet separate effort
beforehand uh to to really develop that
dispassion to the point where their
minds could really just see sensal
pleasure for what they are simply on
account of hearing a discourse but for
most of us today we are so far down the
Deep the the rabbit hole of U of
sensuality that you know even
just years of of practice is not
necessarily enough in fact even becoming
a mck is not even a guarantee that your
mind will actually be withdrawn from
from sensuality because the Buddha said
in another suta that
um we'll try to to link the relevant
sutas in the in the comment section uh
he said that it doesn't matter like how
many external observances a person might
adhere to uh fundamentally if internally
there is still that value that I
mentioned that that that um leaning
towards the the the possibility of
sensuality anytime in the future even if
it's in the next life the mind is not
free from sensal desire and uh
so uh and because of that uh it won't
actually be able to give rise to true
knowledge simply on account of that so
he gave a simile that it's like two wet
sticks that you you you try to use them
to make a fire but obviously because
they're wet you know you can't even
light a spark with them uh so you
actually need to dry out the sticks
first and then you can light the fire so
lighting the fire in that case refers to
U you know the getting the right view
pretty much so uh all that is just
pointing to the fact that the Mind needs
to be in internally uh dispassionate
toward sensuality in order to uh
actually understand the dhma because
basically the value the valuing of of
sensuality is like the most the coarsest
the the most
um the most hindering way of of not
seeing the second Noble Truth so
everyone wants to be free from Pain and
to the degree that they still regard
sensuality as a as a potential solution
to that problem they're not seeing the
second Noble Truth it's that simple so
any attempt to see it even hearing even
like hearing a discourse from the Buddha
himself won't really make a difference
so but obviously um you know the
the the argument that is made and
there's in fact another suta where where
there's this Layman who is um already a
stream mentor and he's drinking so he's
breaking uh he's breaking even the basic
five precepts and uh you know the people
were criticizing him in the Buddha uh
explain to them that um no even though
he's he's drinking he's still a stre
murer uh because he actually understood
the the formable truth so obviously the
the the there is a truth in the sense
that um once you understand the dhma you
can afford to not be restrained uh but
the problem is that before that if you
allow yourself the the the possibility to uh
yourself the the the possibility to uh
not just engage but value sensuality
even if you're not uh even if you're
you're not engaging with it for example
as a monk you're limited from engaging
with sensuality but internally you can
very much be valuing it so if that value
is not giving up given up um you won't
be able to get the right view which
means non-restraint is something very
non-restraint is something very
different like from from what's
Happening uh internally let's say when a
stream ENT is not restrained so there is
a there is like a
huge immense difference between what's
internally happening uh in a stream
Mentor when they when they say break the
five precepts and what's happening uh in
AJ who doesn't have the right view
because fundamentally like it's
no matter how much a stream ment might
stray away from the path the fact is
they see the path with a perfect um
certainty so they can reestablish that
with which they acquired pretty much in
a finger snap as a as as like as an act
of will but for for whenever ajena
engages with sensuality what they're
doing is essentially like sinking deeper
in a hole that they already don't know
how to get out of so that's what
happening when somebody who doesn't have
the right view
before uh having the Right View engages
with sensuality and there's actually
another simile where the developed mind
let's say of a stream Mentor is is
compared to the great ocean uh where if
if you were to dump even a a big load of
salt it wouldn't really change anything
whereas the undeveloped mind is like a
little glass of water where where even
just a bit of salt is going to make a
very noticeable difference so that that
salt is basically like the external um
you know breaches of restraint that one
might have uh they are very polluting in
the case of a puga but in the case of a
a stream enter they they might hardly
make a difference so expanding the mind
up to that great ocean with the little
glass of water that you start off with
is done through uh saying no to your
desires it's not done through focusing
on one object which is basically taking
you in the opposite direction narrowing
the Mind down and uh saying no to your
desires expands the mind because the
only reason why you feel that impulse to
say yes by default is because the mind
is already tnal visioned towards those
things it's already completely
constricted but obviously you don't even
recognize that that doesn't have to be
that way because you've been living that
way since forever and then when you
justify to yourself that you don't have
to give it up you're just
justifying that little glass of water
that you have and not going going beyond
that there's even one suta where the
Buddha says that the cause for the five
hindrances is misconduct of body speech
and mind you will never find a s saying
that it's the inability to focus on one
object and the issue is not so much like
the fact that your let's say your virtue
and your restraint is not perfect right
of the bat the main problem is the view
that you don't have to be restrained
because as the Buddha said view like the
wrong view is the most pernicious of all
things even worse than than you know if
there are every now and then slips in
your behavior but you were genuinely
trying the the really bad thing is when
you have a view that what you're doing
is Justified or is fine that you don't
have to be restrained because that's not
that's not in the contract when you're a
Layman um so
um that's that's the thing that that
that um people don't really see so even
if like sure being you can get the right
view as layment but it's not what what
you have to differentiate is uh the
state of a Layman who doesn't have the
right View and and the state of layman
who does so and uh the process that
those people
underwent in let's
say an hour or a few or or 45 minutes of
talking to the Buddha to the point where
their mind became internally withdrawn
from from the hindrances that process
today would take is what would take
years for a person because that's how
much more um uh pollution there is in
the mine due to previous habits and and
and all that so um that's that that's
that additional um baggage that we carry
that they didn't have back then and and
uh like you in fact you don't even see
people in the sutas uh struggling to get
the right view the way we do today like
people who were heard the Buddha for the
first time developed real faith in the
teaching and yet they were unable for
some reason to get the right view the
way it happens today everyone back then
who got the right view um was was like
it was basically as soon as they
recognized that the dma is a true way
they got The Right View as soon as they
acknowledge that that they sort of
converted to to the teaching they got
the right view um um the other people
who didn't you can see like there was
for example this king posinadi who uh he
he did respect the Buddha he gave
offerings and stuff but he was still uh
agreeing to some extent with the views
of other teachers which which means he
hadn't actually accepted fully the the
um the rightness of the dhama so he's
one of the people who didn't get the
right view even though he talked to the
Buddha many times but the point I'm
making is you don't see like these the
way you see today like people who are
genuinely devoted uh to the dma they they they
devoted uh to the dma they they they
don't have any sort of
um like they're giving it their allw and
yet they fail after an entire lifetime
of of trying to get the right view that
didn't happen back then so that is uh
just evidence of the fact that that uh
you know their minds were in a different
position than than ours are today so
that process that that uh of a few
minutes of listening to the Buddha for
you to get to that point where your mind
is truly dispassionate toward cality
you're going to have to actually give up
uh the the that value and most
especially the ways in which you are
manifesting that value in the world so
the actual actions through body and
speech that are that are uh making it
clear that you still value um sensuality
as a potential solution to to the issue
of suffering
um and
um that that is
um in
essence that training is is the gradual
training that we often talk about um you
know virtue sense restraint moderation
eating watchfulness of your intentions
and all that stuff so
um and and especially the the the the
reason why we say you you need to take
up that gradual training
uh and and really give your 100% to it
is that
um precisely like the the the main
characteristic of the state of PJ is
that you don't even see what the problem
is you don't even see the size of your
ignorance to put it that way so whenever
you decide or or say say to yourself
that or
Justify giving up only a partial
amount there's like a
99.99999% chance that that what you're
not giving up is exactly what you needed
to give up in order to truly um purify
your mind from all these obstructions so
that's another Su the Buddha said it's
like it's like a quail who is tied with
a with a with like a rotten rope and it
says well this is fine this is just a
rotten rope I can I can break out of it
at any time but because it's a quail it
can't actually even though technically
it's a weak rope it can't break out of
it uh so that's that's like when people
think oh this is fine I'm not actually
attached to all these things well if
that were if that were the case you you
wouldn't be so uh insistent on the fact
that uh and you wouldn't get so
defensive when people tell you that that
you need to give it up in fact if you're
truly confident that that that giving up
cality is for your welfare which is the
direction of nibana in general giving up
of craving uh which is the confidence
that a streem has you wouldn't have any
problem with with at least the idea that
you need to give it up you would only
not give it up if you accept that at the
moment you're not practicing and that's
one thing that that people fail to see
as well in that suta of the Layman
sakani who was um who was drinking as a
true Mentor is the Buddha said at the
very end of the suta that this man um
undertook the training at the time of
death so the the the key there is he
death because he was not training before
that so even though he was he was a
Sherer he had understood the dhama he
had the perfect right
meditation uh as opposed to you know
what what people do today uh even he was
not able to have that right View and
that right understanding right effort uh
right composure all these things apart
from his actual Behavior so giving up
the the restraint meant giving up the
training even for him so that's why the
Buddha said only at the time of death
when he didn't have the chance to be
careless anymore he undertook the
training again so what is then to be said of
again so what is then to be said of
somebody who doesn't even have those
those uh wholesome qualities those
wholesome factors and they allow
themselves to to cultivate the opposite
of them so um there's just I mean it's
shooting ones in the foot ultimately and
um
the the other thing to recognize as well
is that the the main characteristic of a
stream Mentor or any Noble disciple uh
the Buddha list of the five faculties uh
and the the first two of them are a
sense of Shame and fear of
wrongdoing and what that means is not
just towards random stuff but towards un
wholesome States that's what the Su says
so they are they have a sense of Shame
and fear of wrongdoing in regard to UNH
wholesome States so
that is part of that big gap that I was
talking about between when somebody who
has a right view engages with with
essential pleasures and distractions and
somebody who doesn't is that that
fundamental sense of Shame is or the
lack of that sense of shame because they
don't they don't know UNH wholesome as
un wholesome fully is what defines the
engagement of the PJ it is a defining
Factor so that's why you can't say that
even you can't say that the the
enjoyment that a stream has the same as
what AJ has because that sense of Shame
is standing behind it all the time so
because again as I said the the view is
the most pernicious thing of all so when
the when the buj is doing it there is a
view there that's not present in the
stre m so even the external actions are
secondary to the fundamental View and
that view is abandoned only by getting
the right view so uh even though you
might see a stream Mentor externally
seemingly doing the same stuff
internally it's not the same because
that if if they were to actually like
just stop for a moment and reflect on
what they're actually doing and just
snap out of it they would immediately
recognize that what they're doing is
wrong they they would be it would be
impossible to have that that
justification of no look I'm I'm a
Layman it's fine you know it's it's this
is what we do no it would be impossible
for them to think that so um the the
that that's what to be to be seen like
as AJ one doesn't one has to tell
oneself I don't
know what it even means to to be free
temporarily free from sensal desire
which is what those people had at that
moment and if I had reached that state
at any point in in in in my practice
with all the amount of knowledge that we
have and and teaching that we've heard I
would have gone the Right View by that
time so you need to you need to
recognize that um
like if you if you really had gone to
the point where those people were you
already got like a thousand times more
instruction that they did so you should
have the right view if at any point in
time your mind was truly dispassionate
towards sensuality eventally this is one
of the biggest pieces of evidence to
show that whatever people usually regard
today as Janna is not actually the real
Janna that the Buddha was teaching
Because the actual Jan is already way
beyond the level of development that
these people had um after which you know
they understood the dma so if a person
today has supposedly been getting Janis
they they should be Way Beyond um uh
those people back in the day
so uh that that just goes to show that
it's it's not even actually taking you
beyond the hindrances which would have
to result in seeing the four noble
truths if you have heard them before and
in such copious amounts as as we have
today and uh you also see in the sutas
that the like the the lay people who
were stre mentors and were still uh not
fully celibate and so on they were not
getting janas so um it's it's it goes to
show that you know if if if it really
were a matter of just applying some
technique then the stream Mentor should
be able to do it very easily uh but they
weren't getting the right uh they
weren't getting janas if you see uh
which late people were getting janas
it's the one who were the ones who were
uh non-r returners and you might think
well they got the janas first and then
um they became non-r returners and then
they became celibate but it's actually
the other way around they got the janas
because they were celibate and that in
the janas made them uh non-
returners so um
the the
um the that one needs to know that
recognize that one doesn't even know
what that state means so or what what
what that um what
that um confidence and renunciation
which is a phrase that the Buddha used
what that even means so any any little
sort of um deviation from at least the
idea you have which is inaccurate but
it's all you have any any willing like
volition deviation from
deviation from
renunciation uh entails uh the risk that
you will never reach that
state um it's as simple as that
so so you could pretty much say that
your situation
today building up the gradual training
in the course of years but allowing
yourself to delight and engage with
sensuality and justify to yourself is
essentially the same as back in the day
when those people were talking to the
Buddha uh if they were to allow
themselves to have sensual thoughts to
regard as pleasant and agreeable that
which he was saying right then and there
it's unsatisfactory and
unbeneficial so in both cases the result
would be that there would be no
penetrative Insight of the for noal
truths despite the fact that it's the
same teaching that you were
hearing and will reach that state
through uh actually you know as we say
um uh practicing gradual training so
it's it's emphatically not a result of a
meditation technique of a Meditation
Retreat for because for example you can
go on a 10-day Retreat and practice as
hard as you can and be celibate and and
keep you know 300 precepts during that
time but if at any point in the future your
but if at any point in the future your
mind is still looking forward to uh to
sensuality then the hindrance of of the
actual hindrance of sensuality is not
abandoned so um it it doesn't it doesn't
it that's why we say it has to be taken
for life for life I will not value
sensuality I will give up the idea that
sensuality is worthwhile for the rest of
my life and then on the basis of that
which you like that idea is not just uh
abstract you have to factually be
implementing it and and really showing
that you actually believe that through
your actions so once that's fully uh
once that's
fulfilled and your life has has been
gone like in concordance with that with
that view then you can actually have a
basis you can have the dry sticks that
might just be able to give rise to the
spark of knowledge and then after that
once you have the right view you can
relax and you can go back to sensuality
but you will realize that it's going
completely different thing uh than any
sort of uh like essential engagement
that you could have had in the past it's
just it's just you you can't
even um you can't even fathom the
difference as AJ uh what it means to be
to be um to to have the right view on
one hand and value nibana and still be
uh engaging with sensuality so because
everything you have is experienced from
the point of view of the wrong view you
can't magically like step out of it for
a moment and imagine how things are for
for a noble disciple
so um that's that's essentially um how
it works and uh
that's that's you another thing that you
need to to to think about is what is the
reason for you not not renouncing things
so yes you like if you have dependence
if you have uh you know a wife that
depends on your children or uh aging
parents then yeah it would be
irresponsible to um you know leave them
and potentially make them have a hard
time but uh does that mean that you need
to engage in sexual intercourse in order
to take care of your dependence does it
mean you you need to have um you know
you need to work extra to get more
wealth than is really necessary
uh to take care of those people uh do
you need to be seeking out uh Pleasant
sights sounds mouths tastes and touches
that are just for the sake of of of
gratification no so uh you you don't you
don't have to do any of these things but
but people often conflate the idea of
yes I can't become a monk with oh okay
so it's fine to to do all the other
stuff uh that that lay people usually do
and that's not the case so even though
again like many of those people in the
sutas You could argue uh you know they
were they didn't
ordain and uh they were also having
sexual intercourse or whatever uh the
point is again they were sh Mentor so
there's a very different thing going on
there and lastly it's important to note
that abandoning sensuality is not
necessary because it's otherwise you're
violating some sort of commandment or
sacred rule it's because it's part and
parcel of the same path towards
attaining one's own welfare so if
abandoning sensuality was not for the
sake of One's Own welfare the Buddha
wouldn't have instructed anyone to do
it so what will happen if you're not
willing to take unrust that abandoning
sensuality is for for your welfare is
that you will instead take up the first
you know watered down version of the
dhma that allows you to seeming
seemingly offers you the same
thing uh
or so you think while at the same time
allowing you to engage with those very
things that are obstructing true Insight
from uh from taking place so the results
of that are going to be uh you know not
the actual uh fundamental Freedom that
the Buddha was teaching like he said
it's it's the suffering that's left for
a streem mure is like um seven grains of
sand compared to the great Mountain that
that was there before uh it's just going
to be some sort of management
method that might make you feel like
there are no grains of sand left at the
moment but uh so seemingly better but in
the end it's only because you're
ignoring that there is a great mountain
behind you that's why it always uh
revolves around all that focusing and
and concentration uh ignoring the full truth
concentration uh ignoring the full truth
pretty much in order to feel a relief so
um it's in fact precisely because the
the actual understanding of the dama
frees you completely to the point where
suffering can't even arise even if you
want it to arise that these people were
able to pretty much give up the training
like completely just
um uh get careless on the surface and
and go on with their lives as as if
nothing happened uh because it's it's
actually like applying to that core of
your existence whereas um you know what
people teach today is just a just a
management method that's going to wear
away within a few weeks if you stop
doing it so that's why people are always
afraid of giving it up uh and and it's
it's just reinforcing that clinging to
to Virtue and
practices so in the end the results will
speak for themselves